I've completely automated my social media posts using MAKE. Just check the automatically gathered content, and AI will craft posts for each platform.
자동으로 수집된 글에 체크만 한번 눌러주면 AI가 각 플랫폼에 맞는 글을 이렇게 완성해줍니다.
It even handles the posting for me.
거기다 포스팅까지 알아서 해줍니다.
Makes social media posting so much easier, right?
SNS 글쓰기가 진짜 쉬워지겠죠?
Lately, you've probably heard that social media marketing is no longer optional, but essential.
여러분 요새 SNS 마케팅이 더 이상 선택이 아닌 필수라는 얘기 많이 들어보셨죠?
Many ordinary workers are now making as much from their social media activity after work as they do from their primary job.
실제로 요즘은 평범한 직장인들도 퇴근 후 SNS 활동만으로 본업 연봉만큼 수익을 올리는 사례들이 상당히 많은데요.
Social media seems to be the best way to build your personal brand or create a side hustle.
그만큼 셀프 브랜딩을 하거나 향후 부업으로 활용하기에 정말 SNS는 최고의 수단인 것 같습니다.
However, those of you who have tried it know that managing social media is not easy.
하지만 SNS 운영이 결코 쉽지 않다는 걸 경험해보신 분들은 잘 아실 거예요.
It's quite a burden to constantly come up with new ideas and create posts tailored for each platform.
매일같이 새로운 아이디어를 떠올리고 각 플랫폼의 특성에 맞춰 포스팅하는 게 여간 부담스러운 일이 아니죠.
But, did you know that overseas marketers are already using AI automation systems to operate their social media accounts and achieve great results, without lifting a finger?
그런데 여러분 해외 마케터들은 이미 AI 자동화 시스템을 활용해서 손 하나 까딱하지 않고 SNS를 운영하면서 큰 성과를 내고 있다는 사실 알고 계신가요?
Yes.
네.
Many of them are easily publishing more than one post per day.
1일 1포스팅은 물론 그 이상의 콘텐츠 발행도 거뜬히 해내고 있는 분들이 많습니다.
Today, I'll show you how to set up a system that automatically posts on your social media accounts with just one setup.
그래서 오늘은 단 한 번만 설정해두면 SNS 게시글이 자동으로 포스팅되도록 하는 시스템을 만드는 방법을 알려드릴까 하는데요.
With this AI automation system, you can automatically handle the entire process, from gathering the latest news, writing the posts, to posting them.
이 AI 자동화 시스템을 활용하면 최신 뉴스 수집부터 게시글 작성 그리고 포스팅까지 이 모든 과정을 자동으로 처리할 수 있습니다.
You can finally achieve your dream of posting daily, without having to worry about what to write.
매일 뭘 써야 할까 고민하던 때에서 벗어나 꿈꾸던 1일 1포스팅을 실현할 수 있는 것이죠.
If you watch till the end, I’ll provide templates, detailed prompt examples, and even show you how I apply this in my work
영상을 끝까지 시청하시면 이 자동화 시스템을 그대로 적용할 수 있도록 템플릿과 상세한
so that you can implement this automation system right away.
프롬프트 예시 그리고 제가 어떻게 실무에 적용하고 있는지까지 모두 알려드리고 있으니까요.
So, please watch till the end.
끝까지 시청해주시기 바랍니다.
Note that while this video focuses on LinkedIn and Twitter, you can also apply this to Instagram or other social media channels.
참고로 이 영상은 링크드인과 트위터를 기준으로 말씀드리지만 인스타그램이나 다른 SNS 채널에도 충분히 응용해서 적용이 가능합니다.
Now, let's take a look at the final output and see how this automation system works.
그럼 이 자동화 시스템이 어떻게 작동하는지 최종 결과물을 함께 보면서 설명해 드리겠습니다
This automation system works in three main stages.
이 자동화 시스템은 크게 3단계로 작동하는데요.
First, we'll use Google Alerts to
첫번째로 먼저 구글 알리미라는 걸 사용해서
automatically collect the latest news on your chosen topics from various news sites,
여러 뉴스 사이트로부터 여러분이 원하는 주제의 최신 뉴스를
and save them to Google Sheets.
구글 시트에 자동으로 저장합니다.
Then, among the collected news, you select the articles you want to post on social media.
그리고 이 수집된 뉴스들 중에 여러분이 SNS에 포스팅하고 싶은 뉴스를 선택해서
When you check the checkbox, ChatGPT will automatically turn them into social media posts.
체크박스를 누르면 ChatGPT가 이걸 알아서 SNS 글로 바꿔줄 거고요.
Lastly, if you like the post that ChatGPT wrote, click the publish button
마지막으로 ChatGPT가 작성한 글이 마음에 들면 옆에 발행 버튼을 눌러서
to automatically post it to your social media accounts.
실제 SNS에 자동으로 포스팅까지 할 수 있습니다.
Of course, you can set this up so that the entire process runs fully automatically, without having to check any boxes.
물론 이 모든 과정을 체크박스를 누를 필요도 없이 완전 자동으로 진행되도록 설정할 수도 있는데요.
I’ll explain this part in detail later.
이 부분은 나중에 자세히 설명 드릴 예정입니다.
Although there's a fully automated method, I recommend using the checkbox method first.
완전 자동화하는 방법도 있지만 먼저 이 체크박스를 쓰는 방식을 추천하는 이유는
Because it allows for more natural writing.
좀 더 자연스러운 글 작성이 가능하기 때문입니다.
By going through this check box process until the prompt is refined,
프롬프트가 어느 정도 다듬어질 때까지는 이렇게 체크박스로 확인하는 단계를 거침으로써
you can produce posts that sound like they were written by a person.
사람이 쓴 것 같은 글로 완성할 수 있을 거예요.
We will build this automation system using a site called make.com.
우리는 이 자동화 시스템을 make.com이라는 사이트를 활용해서 만들 예정인데요.
If you're new to make.com, you can sign up through the link in the description or the pinned comment.
make.com을 처음 써보시는 분들은 설명란 또는 고정 댓글을 통해서 make.com에 가입하실 수 있으니까 참고해주세요.
Let's start with the first step in social media automation: setting up Google Alerts.
그럼 이제 SNS 자동화의 첫 단계인 구글 알리미 설정부터 시작하도록 하겠습니다.
Through Google Alerts, we can gather news articles daily via RSS.
이 구글 알리미를 통해서 RSS로 매일 뉴스 기사들을 수집할 수가 있는데요.
Some of you may be unfamiliar with the concept of RSS.
RSS라는 개념이 좀 생소하신 분들도 있으실 것 같아요.
RSS is a technology that allows users to receive new content
RSS는 사용자가 웹사이트에 들어가서 매일 경제에 직접 방문하지 않고도
without having to visit the website directly.
새로운 콘텐츠를 받아볼 수 있게 해주는 기술입니다.
Many news sites and blogs offer their own RSS feeds.
많은 뉴스 사이트나 블로그들이 자체적으로 RSS 피드를 제공하고 있는데요.
For example, if you subscribe to the Maeil Business Newspaper's RSS feed,
예를 들어서 매일 경제에 RSS를 구독하면
you can receive the latest news alerts without visiting their website.
이 매일 경제 사이트에 방문하지 않고도 최신 뉴스 알림을 받아볼 수 있는 거죠.
While you can get RSS feeds from each news site,
각각의 뉴스 사이트에서 RSS를 따올 수도 있지만
Google Alerts allows you to skip visiting each of those sites.
구글 알리미는 이러한 각각의 사이트에 들어갈 필요 없이
It’s very useful because you just set keywords here, and it gathers all the news on the topics you're interested in.
여기 키워드만 설정하면 내가 관심 있는 주제에 대한 뉴스들을 다 수집을 해주기 때문에 굉장히 유용합니다.
Visit the Google Alerts website and search for the keywords you want.
여기 구글 알리미 사이트에 들어가서 여러분이 원하는 키워드를 검색을 해주면
The latest news related to those keywords will appear.
해당 키워드와 관련된 최신 뉴스들이 나타납니다.
I'll search for "AI".
저는 AI로 한번 검색을 해볼게요.
When you search, you'll see a list of AI-related news.
이렇게 검색을 하면 AI 관련 뉴스들이 쭉 뜨게 되고요.
If you want to collect this news, click "Create Alert" at the top.
이 뉴스들을 수집하고 싶다면 상단에 알림 만들기를 눌러주시면 됩니다.
Then, click the pencil icon,
그리고 여기 연필 부분을 눌러서
change the "Deliver to" option to "RSS feed" and click "Update Alert."
수신 위치를 RSS 피드로 바꿔주시고 알림 업데이트를 눌러줍니다.
An antenna icon will appear next to the AI keyword.
그러면 이 AI라는 키워드 옆에 이 전파 아이콘이 생기는데요.
Clicking this icon will take you to the RSS news feed address, which is in XML format.
이 전파 아이콘을 누르면 XML로 구성된 RSS 뉴스 피드 주소로 이동합니다.
Select the entire address in the address bar, and press Ctrl+C to copy it.
이 주소창의 주소를 전체 선택 후 Ctrl C를 눌러서 복사를 해주세요.
Now, let's build an automation system using make.com.
이제 본격적으로 make.com을 활용한 자동화 시스템을 구축을 해볼게요.
When you log in to make.com, you will see the same screen as mine.
먼저 make.com에 로그인하면 저 같은 화면이 뜨실 텐데요.
Click the "Scenarios" button on the left,
왼쪽에 시나리오 버튼을 눌러주시고
and click "Create a new scenario" at the top right to create a new scenario.
여기 오른쪽 위에 Create New Scenario를 눌러서 새로운 시나리오를 생성해주세요.
First, let's create a scenario to gather news.
일단 뉴스를 수집하는 시나리오를 만들 건데요.
I've already prepared a JSON file to some extent in my YouTube description.
제 유튜브 설명란에 미리 JSON 파일을 어느 정도 만들어 뒀거든요.
Let’s start with that.
그걸 바탕으로 시작을 해보겠습니다.
First, download the JSON file from the YouTube description.
제 유튜브 설명란에 있는 JSON 파일을 먼저 다운받아 주시고요.
Those of you who have downloaded the file, click the "..." at the bottom of the scenario,
다운받으신 분들은 여기 시나리오 하단에 ...을 눌러서
and click "Import Blueprint".
Import Blueprint를 눌러주시고
Upload the downloaded file and click "Save."
다운받으신 파일을 업로드해주시고 세이브를 눌러주시면
You'll see a screen like this.
저처럼 이런 화면이 뜨실 겁니다.
Click on the RSS news collection part.
여기서 RSS 뉴스 수집 이 부분을 클릭을 해주시고요.
You will see the same options window as mine. Paste the feed address we created earlier into the URL part by pressing Ctrl+V.
저 같은 옵션 창이 보이실 건데 이 URL 부분에 아까 만든 피드 주소를 Ctrl V로 붙여넣어 주시고요.
This will collect AI news.
이렇게 하면 AI 뉴스들이 수집이 될 겁니다.
"Date From" and "Date To" are where you enter the date range for the news to collect.
Date From과 Date To는 언제부터 언제까지의 뉴스를 가져올 건지 입력하는 칸인데요.
Currently, it's set to "Now" and "-6", which means it will gather the news from now to 6 days ago.
지금 같은 경우는 Now 그리고 마이너스 6으로 되어 있으니까 현재부터 6일 전까지의 뉴스를 가져오겠다고 되어 있는 겁니다.
I'll change 6 to 1, so it will only get the news from today until yesterday.
여기서 저는 6을 1로 바꿔서 오늘부터 어제까지의 뉴스만 가져와 보도록 할게요.
Below, you will see the "Maximum Number of Returned Items" section.
그리고 밑에 보면 Maximum Number of Returned Items라고 적혀있는데
This is where you set the number of news to gather at once.
이건 한 번에 몇 개의 뉴스를 가져올 거냐를 설정하는 부분입니다.
It's currently set to gather a maximum of 5 news articles.
지금은 뉴스를 5개까지만 가져오는 걸로 설정이 된 거고요.
Keep these settings and click "OK" to save.
이렇게 설정을 두고 OK를 눌러주시면 저장됩니다.
Clicking "Run Once" at the bottom will execute this scenario. Let's click it.
하단에 Run Once 버튼을 누르면 이 시나리오가 실행되거든요. 한 번 눌러보겠습니다.
Click "Run Anyway".
Run Anyway를 눌러주시면 되고요.
Wait a moment after clicking, and a white circle will appear at the top, just like mine.
누르고 잠시 기다리시면 저처럼 여기 위쪽에 흰색 동그라미가 뜰 텐데요.
Click the white circle above the "RSS news collection" section,
이 RSS 뉴스 수집 위에 흰색 동그라미를 클릭을 해보면
and you can see what news has been collected.
실제로 어떤 뉴스가 수집되어 있는지 볼 수가 있습니다.
You can see that a total of five news articles have been gathered: Bundle 1, Bundle 2, and Bundle 3.
보면은 Bundle 1부터 Bundle 2, Bundle 3 해서 총 5개의 뉴스가 가져와진 걸 볼 수 있고요.
Inside each bundle, you can see the title of the news, an overview of the news,
각 번들 안에 보면은 뉴스의 제목, 그리고 뉴스의 개요,
and the URL has also been collected.
URL도 가져와진 거를 볼 수가 있습니다.
Importantly, we only have the news titles and URLs, but not the news content.
여기서 중요한 게 저희가 지금 뉴스 제목이랑 URL만 있고 뉴스 본문이 없어요.
To gather the main content, we need to access the URL and get the actual article content.
본문을 가져오려면 이 URL로 접속을 해서 실제 기사 내용을 가져와야 되는데
However, the problem is that this URL is not the actual article URL.
문제는 이 URL이 진짜 기사 URL이 아니라는 겁니다.
Let me copy it and show you.
복사해서 한 번 보여드릴게요.
If I copy this and paste it into the internet and check the actual destination,
이걸 복사해서 인터넷 창에 붙여 넣어서 실제로 가는 주소를 확인해보면
you can see that the actual address is this one.
실제 주소는 이 주소인 걸 확인할 수 있거든요.
To clean up the address and make it a direct URL,
그래서 이 주소를 이렇게 깔끔한 주소로 정리를 해주기 위해서
I've added 3 modules in advance on make.com.
이 make .com에 제가 3개의 모듈을 미리 추가를 해뒀는데요.
Each of these modules act like a filter, cleaning up the complex URL step by step.
각각의 모듈이 거름망처럼 작동해서 복잡한 URL을 단계적으로 깔끔하게 정리를 해줄 겁니다.
The first module has this pattern inside.
첫 번째 모듈 같은 경우는 이러한 패턴이 들어가 있는데요.
This is a type of rule called a regular expression.
이게 정규식이라는 일종의 규칙입니다.
This regular expression rule means that in this URL,
이 정규식 규칙은 지금 이러한 URL에서
it will only extract the URL between "URL=" and "&CT."
이 URL "=" 다음 부분부터 &CT 사이에 이 URL만 뽑아낸다는 뜻이거든요.
The second module means it will replace %3D with =.
그리고 두 번째 모듈은 이 %3D를 "="로 바꿔준다는 뜻입니다.
And the third module means that if there is %3F in the URL, it will replace that with a question mark (?).
그리고 세 번째 모듈은 이 URL에서 %3F라는 부분이 있으면 그걸 물음표로 바꿔준다는 뜻이고요.
After these three refining steps,
이렇게 세 번의 정제 작업을 거치면은
it will change into the clean article URL that I showed you earlier.
이렇게 아까 보여드린 것처럼 깔끔한 기사 URL로 바뀌게 됩니다.
Let’s click the white module of "URL Refinement 3,"
실제로 이 URL 정제 3번에 흰색 모듈을 눌러서
then click the "Operation" part, and check the output section.
이 오퍼레이션 부분을 눌러서 아웃풋 부분을 확인을 해보면요.
You can see that the real article URL has been extracted cleanly.
이렇게 깔끔하게 진짜 기사 URL이 뽑혀서 나온 것을 볼 수가 있어요.
Now, let's gather the actual news content using this clean URL.
자 이제 이 깔끔해진 URL로 실제 뉴스 본문을 가져와 볼 겁니다.
Click the plus button, and search for "http".
옆에 플러스를 눌러서 http를 검색해 주시고요.
Then, click "Make a request" and add it.
여기서 Make a request를 눌러서 추가를 해주세요.
When you click on the URL part, the results created by the previous modules will appear.
이 URL 부분에 클릭을 하면은 여기에 이전 모듈들이 만들어낸 결과물들이 쭉 뜹니다.
Think of these boxes marked with different colors as baskets.
여기 이 색깔로 표시된 이 박스들이 하나의 바구니라고 생각을 하시면 돼요.
Each of these baskets contains the information that we need.
각각의 이 바구니 안에 우리가 필요한 정보들이 담겨져 있는 거거든요.
The information that we need to put here,
지금 우리가 여기에 넣어야 될 정보는
is the clean URL that was filtered by URL Refinement 3.
URL 정제 3번의 모듈을 통해서 깔끔하게 걸러진 URL이잖아요.
If you look under URL Refinement 3,
그래서 이렇게 URL 정제 3번 밑을 보면은
you will see a preview of what is contained in that basket.
이 바구니 안에 뭐가 담겨져 있는지 이렇게 미리보기로 보여지게 됩니다.
Because it contains the clean URL,
여기 이렇게 깔끔한 URL이 담겨져 있으니까
click the text basket from URL Refinement 3 to add it.
이 URL 정제 3번의 텍스트 바구니를 눌러서 이렇게 추가를 해주면 되겠죠.
The method will remain as "get" in its current state, which means to get or gather the news.
메소드는 현재 상태 그대로 get으로 두면은 뉴스를 get, 즉 가져온다는 뜻이고요.
Here’s a tip only the pros know.
여기서 고수들만 아는 꿀팁 하나를 드릴게요.
Most sites block scraping of their content
대부분의 사이트들은 자기네 사이트에서 정보를 스크랩하는 걸 막기 위해서
by checking the headers. If it looks like a bot is scraping, they'll block it.
이 헤더를 검사를 해서 로봇이 긁어가는 것 같으면 막아버리거든요.
So, we'll create fake headers to make the site think we're real people.
그래서 우리는 이 사이트가 진짜 사람처럼 착각하도록 가짜 헤더를 만들어줄 겁니다.
In the header section, click "add header."
헤더 부분에 이렇게 add header를 눌러서
Add "cookie" to the name section.
name 부분에 cookie를 추가를 해주시고요.
Click it again,
또 한 번 눌러서
and type "accept."
accept라고 입력을 해주세요.
Click it once more, and this time, type "accept"
그리고 한 번 더 눌러서 이번에는 accept
-Encoding" and add it.
-Encoding이라고 입력을 해주시고
Add another one and type "User-Agent."
한 번 더 추가를 해서 User-Agent라고 추가를 해줍니다.
This will allow us to scrape news from website URLs.
이렇게 하면 웹사이트 URL에서 뉴스를 긁어올 수 있게 될 거예요.
Let's test to see if it scrapes well.
실제로 잘 긁어와지는지 테스트를 해보겠습니다.
Click OK.
ok를 눌러주시고요.
Let's click run once to test it.
밑에 run once를 눌러서 테스트해보겠습니다.
A white circle will appear above the http module.
그러면 이렇게 http 모듈 위에 이렇게 흰색 원이 뜨고
If you click it, you can see that it says 5 news articles and 5 results have been executed.
눌러보면 5개의 뉴스, 5개의 결과가 실행되었다고 이렇게 뜨는 걸 볼 수가 있고요.
Click any operation, and
이 중에서 아무 operation이나 이렇게 눌러보면
you can see that these values were input and these values were output.
input으로 이러한 값들이 들어왔고 이러한 값들이 나왔다 이렇게 출력이 되는 걸 볼 수가 있어요.
If you click the data under the bundle in the output,
여기서 output 아래에 있는 bundle 밑에 있는 데이터를 이렇게 누르면
you can see the entire HTML of the corresponding web page, including the news article, has been scraped.
이렇게 그 해당 웹페이지에 뉴스, 기사를 포함한 html 전체가 이렇게 긁어진 거를 볼 수가 있습니다.
But what we really need is not this entire HTML code, but the content of the news.
그런데 우리한테 진짜 필요한 거는 이 html 코드 전체가 아니라 뉴스 내용이잖아요.
So, we need to extract only the actual text from this HTML code.
그래서 이 html 코드에서 실제 텍스트만 뽑아내야 됩니다.
Let’s add a new module for this.
이걸 위해서 새로운 모듈을 추가할 건데요.
Click the plus button, and search for "Text parser".
플러스를 누르시고 Text parser를 검색을 해주세요.
When you click on Text parser, you'll see an "html to text" module.
이 Text parser를 누르고 보면 html to text라는 모듈이 있습니다.
Click on it. If you insert the html to be converted in the "html" section, it will convert it into text format.
이걸 눌러주시고 이 html 란에다가 바꿀 html을 넣으면 그걸 텍스트 형태로 바꿔주게 됩니다.
Click the empty space, and the results from previous modules will appear, like before.
여기 빈 칸에 마우스를 클릭을 하면 아까처럼 이렇게 이전 모듈의 결과 값이 쭉 뜨는데요.
What we need is the results from this http module, this data value.
여기서 우리가 필요한 건 이 http 모듈에서의 결과 값인 이 데이터 값을 넣으면 되겠죠
Click data to add it, and then click "OK".
데이터를 클릭을 해서 넣어주시고 ok를 눌러줍니다.
Let's run it once.
한번 실행해 보겠습니다.
Click "Run Anyway."
run anyway를 눌러주시고요.
Wait a moment, and the http module will execute. Then, 5 results will appear in the Text parser.
좀 기다리면 이렇게 http 모듈이 실행되면서 이 Text parser에 5개의 결과가 생기고
Click on it. Inside the output, in the text section,
눌러보면 이 아웃풋 안에 텍스트란 안에 보면
you can see that only the text area with the html has been removed.
html이 제거된 텍스트 영역만 쫙쫙 남게 되는 것을 볼 수가 있습니다.
However, if you look at the extracted news in detail,
그런데 추출된 뉴스를 자세히 보면은
what we want is the actual content, but not only the main content.
저희가 여기서 원하는 거는 이 실제 본문인데 본문뿐만 아니라
You can see that it also includes things like sharing options and website menu sections.
이렇게 공유라든지 웹사이트의 메뉴 부분이라든지 이런 부분들도 다 한꺼번에 포함되어 있는 걸 볼 수가 있어요.
Since we only want the main text, let's extract only that part cleanly.
여기서 우리가 원하는 거는 이 텍스트 본문 부분만이기 때문에 이것만 깔끔하게 추출을 해 볼 건데요.
Before that, let’s change the names of the added modules to something easier to understand.
그 전에 이 추가한 모듈 이름도 좀 더 알아보기 쉽게 바꿔주겠습니다.
Right-click on the http module and click "rename".
이 http 모듈에서 마우스 오른쪽을 클릭해서
I'll change it to "Extract News Data".
rename을 눌러서 뉴스 데이터 추출이라고 바꿔줄게요.
And also, rename the "Text parser" and change it to
그리고 Text parser도 rename을 눌러서 이것은
"Convert HTML to Text".
html을 텍스트로 변환이라고 바꿔주겠습니다.
Next, click the plus button beside the module to add a new module.
그 다음에 이 모듈 옆에 플러스를 눌러서 새로운 모듈을 추가할 건데요.
Click "Open AI," and click "Create a Completion."
Open AI를 누르고 여기서 create a compilation을 눌러주세요.
For those who are connecting for the first time, you won't see the connection like me but a button that you can click.
처음 접속하신 분들은 저처럼 이렇게 연결이 된 게 아니라 여기에 버튼 형태로 뜨실 건데요.
The method for connecting is not difficult. I'll leave it in detail in the description.
연결하는 방법은 어렵지 않으니까 설명란에 자세히 남겨둘게요.
Follow that guide to connect, and you'll see the same window as me.
그걸로 연결을 진행을 해주시면 저랑 똑같은 창이 뜰 겁니다.
Now, let’s configure settings to cleanly extract the main body of the news.
자 이제 뉴스 본문을 깔끔하게 뽑아주기 위한 설정을 해 볼게요.
In the options section, select GPT-3.5 for the model.
옵션 부분의 모델에서 GPT-3.5를 선택을 하겠습니다.
I’ll select 3.5 turbo 0125.
3.5 터보 0125를 선택을 할게요.
If you set the model to GPT-4o, the accuracy will improve,
모델을 GPT-4o로 하면은 정확도가 올라가긴 하는데
but the amount of text inside is very large as you saw earlier.
지금 여기 안에 들어있는 텍스트 양이 아까 보셨다시피 굉장히 많잖아요.
So, if you use GPT-4o, the cost will be too high.
그래서 GPT-4o로 하면은 비용이 너무 높아지기 때문에
So, I’ll use the cheaper GPT-3.5 for this.
여기서는 저렴한 GPT-3.5로 쓰겠습니다.
Next, add a message below the Message, and set the role to "user."
그리고 메세지 아래에 add message를 추가를 한 다음에 row를 user로 설정을 해 주시고요.
Then, write this in the text content.
텍스트 콘텐트에 이렇게 적어주세요.
"Remove all parts of this document that are not related to the news."
"이 문서에서 이 뉴스와 관련되지 않은 부분을 모두 제거해줘."
"Only the news title and the news content should remain."
"뉴스 제목과 뉴스 본문만 남겨야 해."
#Document
#문서
And to let ChatGPT know what the topic of this news is, I will add it here.
이렇게 해 주시고 이 ChatGPT가 이 뉴스의 주제가 뭔지 알 수 있게 여기다가 추가를 해 줄게요.
Put parentheses next to the news,
뉴스 옆에다가 괄호를 친 다음에
and add the title of the news from the RSS collection module,
이 안에다가 뉴스의 제목이 담겨있는 이 rss 수집 모듈 하위에
by clicking the title section.
타이틀 부분을 클릭을 해서 추가를 해 주겠습니다.
And also, next to the document, add the news content that we’ll extract,
그리고 문서 옆에도 저희가 추출할 뉴스 내용이 들어 있는
by clicking the text in the html to text conversion module.
이 html 텍스트로 변환 모듈 안에 있는 텍스트를 눌러서 추가를 할게요.
Then, turn on "Show Advanced Settings" below,
그리고 여기 아래에 show advanced settings를 켜서
open the advanced menu, and lower the temperature to about 0.2.
고급 메뉴를 키신 다음에 여기 temperature를 0.2 정도로 줄여 주겠습니다.
The closer this temperature value is to 1, the more creative the response will be.
이 temperature 값이 1에 가까우면 가까울수록 창의적인 답변이 나오고
But since we don't need a creative response at this time, set it to around 0.2, which is close to 0.
지금은 그렇게 창의적인 답변이 필요한 건 아니니까 0에 가까운 0. 2 정도로 설정을 하는 거고요.
"Max completion token" is where you set the length of the response,
그리고 Max completion token은 답변 길이를 설정하는 건데
but I will enter 0 here to have no limitations to the length of the response.
여기서는 답변 길이에 제한을 두지 않기 위해서 0을 입력하겠습니다.
Click "OK," and click "Run Once" again to execute it.
ok를 누른 다음에 다시 한번 run once를 눌러서 실행해 보겠습니다.
Since it costs a lot, let's run only the first one and click stop.
비용이 많이 드니까 처음 첫 번째 것만 실행시키고 stop을 눌러줄게요.
After it executes, click this white bubble at the top of the Open AI
이렇게 실행이 된 다음에 Open AI 상단에 이
to check the result.
흰색 풍선을 눌러서 결과 값을 확인해 보면
You can see that the actual news content has been extracted in the result section.
이 Result 안에 실제 뉴스 본문이 이렇게 추출된 것을 볼 수가 있고요.
Note that, right now, I’m using 3.5-0125, which is the cheapest option.
참고로 지금은 3.5, 0125 가장 비용이 싼 걸로 해가지고
So, the content extraction isn't very accurate.
지금 본문 추출이 아주 정확하게 이루어지진 않았는데요.
The more expensive the model you use, the more accurate the results will be.
조금 더 비싼 모델을 쓸수록 이 결과 값도 아주 정확하게 출력이 되니까
Please consider the cost when you’re setting up your configuration.
그 부분은 가격 부분을 생각을 해서 설정을 해 주시면 되겠습니다.
Now that the news content has been extracted successfully, let's save this content in Google Sheets.
이렇게 뉴스 본문이 잘 출력이 됐으니까 이 본문을 구글 시트에 저장을 해 줄 겁니다.
First, let's create a Google Sheet.
먼저 구글 시트를 만들어 줄게요.
Go to the Google Spreadsheets site, create a blank spreadsheet,
구글 스프레드 시트 사이트에 가서 빈 스프레드 시트를 눌러서 만든 다음에
and name it "News Scrap". Add headers at the top: "Title", "Original URL",
뉴스 스크랩으로 해주고 첫 번째 맨 위에 제목 원문 url
and "Date Posted".
작성일이라고 이렇게 헤더를 넣어줄게요.
Go back to make.com.
다시 make.com으로 돌아와서
Click the plus button to the right of the last Open AI module, and click on the Google Sheets,
이 마지막 Open AI 모듈 오른쪽에 플러스를 눌러서 이 구글 시트를 눌러주시고요.
and select "Add a row".
add a row를 선택을 해 주세요.
I've already linked Google Sheets to my account, so it appears like this.
저 같은 경우는 이미 그 구글 시트와 연동이 되어 있어서 이렇게 뜨는데
But for you, a button will appear.
여러분 같은 경우는 버튼이 뜨실 거예요.
Click that button and log in to connect.
그걸 눌러서 로그인해 주시면 연결이 됩니다.
After connecting, click the button under Spreadsheet ID,
연결을 해 주신 다음에 이 스프레드 시트 아이디 밑에 있는 버튼을 누르셔 가지고
search for the News Scrap that we created earlier, and add it.
아까 만들었던 뉴스 스크랩을 검색을 해 주시고 추가를 해 줍니다.
And for the sheet name, use sheet1. Since we added headers earlier,
그리고 시트 네임은 sheet1 그리고 아까 헤더를 만들었으니까
set the "Headers" option to yes.
헤더 포함 여부 예스로 주시면 되고요.
In the "Values" section, you can put the data that you want to input into Google Sheets.
그리고 이 values 이 부분이 구글 시트에 입력할 데이터를 넣어주면 되는 부분인데요.
Since we need to put the news title in the title column, click on the title under the RSS News Collection module,
이 제목열에 뉴스 제목을 넣어야 될 거니까 이 팝업창에서
in this pop-up window, and add it.
이 rss 뉴스 수집 모듈 밑에 있는 title을 클릭을 해서 입력을 해 주시면 되고요.
Next, we need to add the original news article to the "Original" section.
그다음에 원문 부분에는 뉴스 기사 원문을 넣어야 되니까
In this pop-up window, we extracted the original news content using the Open AI module,
이 팝업창에서 저희가 Open AI 모듈을 통해서 이 뉴스 원문을 추출을 해 줬잖아요.
so add the result value.
이 result 값을 넣어주시면 되겠습니다.
And for the URL section,
그리고 url 란에는
add the text result from the URL Refinement 3 module, which is the cleaned-up version of the URL.
이 url 정제 3번 모듈을 통과해서 깔끔하게 정돈된 url 결과 값 텍스트를 입력을 해 주면 되겠죠.
For the "Date Posted" section, select and add the date created from the RSS news collection module.
그리고 작성일 부분에는 이 rss 뉴스 수집 모듈 밑에 있는 date created
Choose the created date and add it.
작성된 날짜를 선택을 해서 입력을 해 주시면 됩니다.
Click "OK".
ok 를 눌러 주시고요.
Let’s click Run Once to see if it works.
실제로 잘 동작하는지 run once를 눌러 보겠습니다.
Let’s wait for it to finish.
눌러서 실행될 때까지 좀 기다려 보도록 하고요.
Sometimes, errors can occur while it’s executing.
이렇게 실행되는 와중에 이렇게 오류가 뜰 때가 있는데요.
The reason for this error is because it’s exceeding the maximum token count of GPT 3.5.
지금 이 오류가 뜬 이유는 GPT 3.5의 그 최대 토큰 수를 넘어서 그런 거거든요.
In this case, right click and
이럴 때는 여기 마우스 오른쪽을 누른 다음에.
add an error handler.
add error handler를 추가를 해 주시면 됩니다.
You can specify how to handle the error.
이 에러가 발생했을 때 어떻게 처리하는지 적어 주시면 되거든요.
If you select "ignore" in the error handler module,
여기 에러 핸들러 모듈 중에서 ignore를 선택을 해 주시면은
it will ignore the error and continue execution.
해당 오류를 무시하고 계속 실행을 하게 됩니다.
It says that the results for four of the news articles have been executed. Let’s check the "News Scrap" Google Sheet.
4개까지는 지금 결과 값이 다 실행이 되었다고 뜨는데 한번 뉴스 스크랩 구글 시트로 이동을 해 볼게요.
You can see that these four news articles have been successfully scraped.
그러면 이렇게 이렇게 4개의 뉴스가 잘 스크랩 된 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
Now, since we added the error handler, let's run it again and check if it executes properly.
이제 에러 핸들러를 추가를 했으니까. 다시 한번 실행시켜서 잘 실행이 되는지 체크를 해 보겠습니다.
Click "Run Once" and it’s executing.
run once를 눌러주면 이렇게 실행이 되고 있고요.
The first one executed, and the second one too.
첫 번째 실행이 되었고 두 번째 실행이 됐고요.
It says the third one has been completed.
세 번째 실행이 완료되었다고 하고요.
The fourth one has been processed as well.
네 번째 이렇게 잘 처리가 됐고
It has ignored one error and has saved the other four to the "News Scrap" sheet.
에러가 발생한 한 건은 이렇게 무시를 했고 나머지 4개는 이 뉴스 스크랩에 잘 저장을 해 준 거를 볼 수가 있습니다.
So far, we’ve built a flow that gathers news.
이렇게 뉴스를 수집해 주는 플로우를 만들었는데요.
We're done after one more modification.
여기서 한 가지만 더 수정해 주면 완료입니다.
That is, the execution interval of this scenario.
바로 이 시나리오의 실행 간격인데요.
Click the clock icon on the left of the first module.
여기 첫 번째 모듈의 왼쪽 시계 아이콘을 눌러주시고
You can set the execution interval of the scenario here.
여기서 시나리오 실행 간격을 세팅을 할 수가 있습니다.
The default is 15 minutes, as you can see.
기본 값은 보시다시피 15분으로 되어 있는데요.
You can change this execution interval to what you want.
여기서 실행 간격을 여러분이 원하는 간격으로 바꿔주시면 됩니다.
If you want to collect news every morning,
매일 아침마다 뉴스를 수집하기를 원하시면
click below Run Scenario, change the execution interval to "Every Day",
여기 런 시나리오 밑에를 눌러서 실행 간격을 에브리데이로 바꿔주시고
and change the time to the time you want and click OK.
시간을... 원하는 시간으로 바꾸신 다음에 OK를 눌러주시면 됩니다.
Then, it will ask if you want to activate the scenario.
그러면 이렇게 시나리오를 활성화할 거냐 이렇게 뜨는데요.
Click "Activate Scenario" to activate it.
활성화하겠다 액티베이트 시나리오를 눌러주시면
This part will be turned on, and it’s set up to run every day at 4:06 PM.
이 부분이 켜지면서 매일 오후 4시 6분마다 실행되도록 하겠다 이렇게 설정이 완료됩니다.
Now, let's build an automated social media publishing system using the collected news.
자 이제 이 수집한 뉴스들을 바탕으로 sns 자동 발행 시스템을 만들어 볼 건데요.
First, let’s add a header “Convert to Social Media Post” in the Google Sheet.
먼저 구글 시트에 sns 글로 변환이라는 헤더를 추가를 할게요.
And add check boxes below it.
그리고 그 밑에 체크박스를 추가를 해줍니다.
Next to it, type LinkedIn and Twitter.
그리고 이 옆에 링크드인 트위터 라고 이어서 적어줄게요.
When the Convert to Social Media Post checkbox is checked, a LinkedIn post and a Twitter post will be created next to it.
이 sns 글로 변환 체크박스가 체크되면 이 옆에 링크드인용 글과 트위터용 글이 생성되게 할 거예요.
And type "Publish" next to it.
그리고 옆에는 발행이라고 적어주시고요.
Add checkboxes here as well.
여기도 체크박스를 추가를 해줍니다.
If this checkbox is checked, the posts created here will be immediately published.
이 체크박스가 체크되면은 여기에 작성된 글들이 바로 발행되게끔 할 겁니다
First, we need to make sure Make can detect when this checkbox is checked.
먼저 이 체크박스가 체크될 때 메이크에서 감지를 할 수 있도록 해줘야 되는데요.
The connection that allows this is called a webhook.
그 역할을 해주는 연결고리를 웹훅이라고 합니다.
A webhook can be set up using the Google Sheets extension of make.com.
웹훅은 make.com의 구글 시트 확장 프로그램을 활용하면 세팅할 수 있는데요.
In the "Extensions" menu, click "Add-ons", and then "Get add-ons".
확장 프로그램 메뉴에서 부가기능, 부가기능 설치하기를 눌러주시고요.
Search for "make" here,
여기서 메이크를 검색을 하시면
and the extension will appear.
이렇게 확장 프로그램이 뜹니다.
I already have it installed, so it says "Uninstall".
저는 이미 설치가 되어 있어서 제거가 뜨는데
But for you, it will say "Install". Click it to install.
여러분은 설치가 뜨실 거예요. 눌러서 설치를 진행을 해주시고요.
Then, go back to make.com, and click "Create a new scenario" to create a new scenario.
그리고 make.com으로 돌아가서 다시 create a new 시나리오를 눌러서 새로운 시나리오를 생성을 해주세요.
Click the Google Sheet and the "Watch changes" module and add it.
여기서 구글 시트, 워치 체인지스 모듈을 눌러서 이렇게 추가를 해주시고요.
When the webhook section appears, click "Add" next to it to create a new webhook.
이 웹훅 부분이 뜨면 옆에 add를 눌러서 새로운 웹훅을 하나 만들어주세요.
The Webhook URL will appear.
그러면 이렇게 웹훅 URL이 뜨는데요.
Click "Copy Address" to copy it, and go back to Google Sheets.
이걸 copy address를 눌러서 복사를 해주신 다음에 다시 구글 시트로 돌아와서
Click "Extensions", "Make for Google Sheets", and then "Settings" to bring up the sidebar.
확장 프로그램, make for Google sheets, settings를 눌러서 옆에 사이드바를 띄워줍니다.
There's a section where you can enter the Webhook URL.
그러면 여기 웹훅 URL을 적는 칸이 있는데요.
Paste it here using Ctrl+V, and click save to connect.
이 부분에 ctrl v로 붙여넣고 save로 저장을 해주시면 연결이 됩니다.
It will say that the settings have been saved.
이렇게 세팅이 잘 되었다고 뜨고요.
Go back to the make scenario and click "OK".
make 시나리오로 돌아와서 ok를 눌러주세요.
To test, click Run Once at the bottom.
테스트를 해보기 위해서 아래에 run once를 눌러줄게요.
The circle will spin, and it will say that it’s detecting the Google Sheet.
그러면 이렇게 원이 돌아가면서 구글 시트를 감지하고 있다고 뜨고요.
In this state, if you check a checkbox in the Google Sheet,
이 상태에서 구글 시트에서 체크박스를 이렇게 체크를 하면
it will say it has been detected, and the results will appear.
이렇게 감지되었다고 하면서 결과값이 뜹니다.
If you check the content in the output bundle,
여기서 아웃풋 번들 안에 이 내용을 확인해보면
the old value is false, which means the checkbox was unchecked,
old value는 false, 즉 체크박스가 체크가 안 되어 있었는데
and the current value is true, which means the make has successfully detected the change in the checkbox.
지금 value는 true로 체크박스의 변경 사항을 make에서 잘 감지한 것을 확인할 수가 있어요.
Click the range section to open it,
그리고 range 부분을 눌러서 열어보면
you can see that it says that the detection occurred on the second row and fifth column.
이 감지된 사항이 두 번째 행 그리고 다섯 번째 열에서 감지되었다고 이렇게 뜨는데요
If you check the location of the checkbox we checked, you can see it is on the second row and the fifth column.
실제로 저희가 체크한 이 체크박스 위치를 보면 두 번째 행, 다섯 번째 열이 맞죠?
You can see that it has been detected successfully.
이렇게 잘 감지를 한 걸 확인할 수가 있습니다.
Now that we’ve verified that the webhook is working correctly, let’s continue.
웹훅이 정상적으로 작동하는 걸 확인했으니까 이어서 만들어보겠습니다.
Click the plus button next to the module, and add "Router" which is in "Flow control".
모듈 옆에 플러스를 눌러서 flow control 안에 있는 Router를 추가해 주시고요.
If you add it, you'll see that it divides into two paths.
추가하면 이렇게 길이 두 개로 나눠지는데요.
The top path will be the flow for when the "Convert to Social Media Post" checkbox is checked, where the post will be written,
위쪽으로는 sns 글 변환 체크박스를 체크하면 글이 써지는 플로우,
and the bottom path will be the flow for when the Publish checkbox is checked, where the post will be published.
아래쪽으로는 발행 체크박스를 체크하면 글이 발행되는 플로우를 만들어볼게요.
Right click on the top line, and click "Set up a filter" to open the filter window.
이 위쪽 선에서 마우스 오른쪽 버튼을 누른 다음에 Set up a filter를 눌러서 이 필터 창을 띄워주시고요.
Since this path should be executed when the "Convert to Social Media Post" checkbox is checked,
SNS 글 변환 체크박스를 눌렀을 때 여기가 실행되어야 하니까
create a rule where the old value is false, and the current value is true.
올드 밸류가 false이고 여기 밸류 값이 true이라는 규칙을 만들어주시면 되고요.
Then, add another "and rule", and click "Column start".
그리고 end를 하나 더 추가한 다음에 Column start를 눌러주시고요.
The checkbox that we're trying to configure is in the first, second, third, fourth, and fifth column.
지금 저희가 설정하려는 이 체크박스 위치가 하나, 둘, 셋, 넷, 다섯 번째 열이죠?
So, put 5 in the column start section.
그러니까 여기 Column start 부분에 5를 넣어주시고
Then, add another "and rule", and add 5 in the column end section as well.
end를 하나 더 추가해서 칼럼 end도 똑같이 5로 추가를 해줍니다.
Click "OK".
OK를 눌러주시고요.
With this, this flow will only be executed when the "Convert to Social Media Post" checkbox is checked.
이렇게 하면 SNS 글 변환 체크박스를 체크할 때만 이 플로우가 실행되게 될 겁니다.
Next, click the plus button and select "Open AI Create a Completion".
그 다음에 이 뒤에 플러스를 눌러서 Open AI Creator Completion을 선택을 해주시고요.
I'll select the GPT-4o Mini for the model.
모델을 GPT-4o Mini로 선택을 하겠습니다.
Click "Add Message", and set the role to "User".
그리고 Add Message를 눌러서 롤은 User로 세팅을 하고요.
In the Text content section, copy and paste the prompt from the YouTube description.
이 Text content 부분에는 유튜브 설명란에 있는 프롬프트를 복사해서 붙여넣어주세요.
This prompt is to ask ChatGPT, acting as a marketer, to create good LinkedIn and Twitter posts.
이 프롬프트는 ChatGPT에게 마케터 역할을 맡겨서 링크드인 글과 트위터 글을 잘 써달라고 부탁하는 글인데요.
When we ask ChatGPT, we need to provide the news content to be converted into social media posts.
ChatGPT에게 부탁할 때 SNS 글로 바꿔줄 기사 원문을 넣어줘야 되니까
So, we'll add the original news content after the "Read and Analyze" section.
여기 읽고 분석하세요. 이 다음 부분에 기사 원문을 넣을 건데요.
If we check where the original news content is in Google Sheet, we can see that it’s in the second column.
이 구글 시트에 기사 원문이 어디 있나 확인을 해보면 두 번째 열에 있는 걸 확인할 수 있습니다.
So, in this pop-up window, click the B column, which is the second column in "Row Value", and add it.
그래서 여기 팝업창에서 Raw Value 안에 두 번째 열인 B열을 눌러서 추가를 해주시면 됩니다.
Also, to display the source, we'll also add the URL next to the original link.
그리고 출처도 함께 표기하기 위해서 URL도 이 원문 링크 옆부분에 넣어줄 건데요.
If we check where the URL is in the Google Sheet again, we can see it is in the third column.
다시 구글 시트에서 URL이 어디에 있나 확인을 해보면 세 번째 열에 있는 걸 확인할 수 있으니까
So, in the prompt section, enter the third column, which is the C column, in this pop-up window.
여기 프롬프트 부분에 팝업창에서 세 번째 열인 C열을 입력을 해주시면 됩니다.
Then, scroll down and set the "Max Tokens" to about 1000.
그리고 밑으로 내려서 이 Max Tokens는 한 1000 정도로 설정을 하겠습니다.
Then, turn on "Show Advanced Settings" below.
그리고 이 아래에 Show Advanced Settings를 켠 다음에
And set the temperature to about 0.32.
이 Temperature는 0.32 정도로 세팅을 하겠습니다.
Leave the rest as the default, and click OK.
나머지는 기본값 그대로 두고 OK를 눌러주시면 되고요.
Click "Run Once" to test it.
Run Once를 눌러서 테스트를 해볼게요.
Go to the Google Sheet,
구글 시트로 이동을 한 다음에
check the checkbox next to the news you want to post, and go back to the Make scenario.
글로 쓰고 싶은 뉴스 옆에 체크박스를 체크를 해서 해 주고 다시 메이크 시나리오로 돌아와 보면
You can see that it has detected the change, and the input was entered into ChatGPT which is writing the post.
이렇게 변화를 감지하고 ChatGPT로 인풋이 들어와서 이렇게 글을 써주는 것을 볼 수 있어요.
If you check the result value,
결과값을 확인을 해 보면
in the "Output" section, click "Result", and you can see that a LinkedIn post,
이 아웃풋 부분에 Result를 눌러보면 이렇게 링크드인 글과
and a Twitter post were created.
트위터 글이 잘 써진 거를 확인을 할 수 있습니다.
We will add the LinkedIn post to the LinkedIn column in the Google Sheet.
여기서 링크드인 글 부분은 구글 시트 링크드인 열에
And we will add the Twitter post to the Twitter column in the Google Sheet.
그리고 트위터 부분은 여기 구글 시트 트위터 열 부분에 추가를 해 줄 건데요.
Since the two posts are combined into one, we will use a tool called a regular expression to separate them.
지금은 두 글이 하나로 합쳐져 있기 때문에 분리해 주기 위해서 정규식이라는 도구를 사용을 할 겁니다.
As mentioned earlier, a regular expression is
정규식은 아까 말씀드렸다시피
a type of formula that extracts the parts of the text that we want.
텍스트에서 우리가 원하는 부분만 뽑아내는 일종의 수식이라고 생각하시면 되는데요.
Click the plus button next to Open AI,
여기 Open AI 옆에 플러스를 눌러서
and select "Match Pattern" under "Text parser."
Text parser 밑에 있는 매치 패턴을 선택을 해 주세요.
Copy and paste the regular expression pattern that I've uploaded in the pinned comment, here.
그리고 여기에 제가 유튜브 고정 댓글에 올려둔 정규식 패턴을 복사 붙여넣기 해 주시면 되고요.
And change "Global match" to "Yes".
그리고 글로벌 매치만 예스로 바꿔주시면은,
It will search the text from beginning to the end, and find all values that match this pattern.
텍스트를 처음부터 끝까지 검색해서 이 패턴과 겹치는 모든 값을 찾아 줄 겁니다.
Then, in the "Text" section, add the "Result" value that ChatGPT created earlier.
그리고 텍스트 부분에 방금 전에 ChatGPT가 만든 Result 결과 값을 입력을 해 줍니다.
Click OK, and click Run Once again to test it.
OK를 눌러 주고 다시 한번 테스트를 위해 Run Once를 눌러 줄게요.
Click "Run Anyway".
Run Anyway를 눌러 주시고요.
Then go back to the Google Sheet, and check the checkboxes next to the news that you want to write about.
그리고 구글 시트로 돌아가서 글로 쓰고 싶은 뉴스 옆 부분에 체크박스를 체크를 해 줍니다.
When you come back here, you can see that Open AI has created the post,
그리고 이렇게 돌아오면은 Open AI가 글을 써 주고,
and the text parser has separated the posts into two parts,
이 글을 Text parser가 두 개로 나눠 가지고 이렇게
a LinkedIn post and a Twitter post.
링크드인 글과 트위터 글로 분리를 해 준 것을 확인을 할 수가 있습니다.
Now, let's save these posts into the Google Sheet.
이제 이 글들을 구글 시트에 저장해 줄게요.
Click the plus button next to the Text parser, and select "Flow Control".
Text parser 옆에 플러스를 눌러서 Flow Control 를 선택을 해 주시고요.
We will add a filter so that the LinkedIn post is saved in the upper path, and the Twitter post is saved in the bottom path.
위쪽에는 링크드인 게시물 아래쪽에는 트위터 게시물이 저장되도록 필터를 걸어 주겠습니다.
If you look at the results from this text parser,
아까 이 Text parser의 결과물을 보면은
you can see that the first LinkedIn post says "i = 1", and the second Twitter post says "i = 2".
첫 번째 링크드인 글 같은 경우는 i가 1이라고 나왔고, 두 번째 트위터 글은 i가 2라고 나왔거든요.
We will use this to set the filter.
이걸 기준으로 필터를 걸어 줄게요.
Click the first line, turn on the filter, click "i" in the pop-up window, and type 1.
여기 첫 번째 선을 눌러서 필터를 켜신 다음에 팝업에서 i를 누르고 1을 입력을 합니다.
Click "OK".
ok 를 눌러 주시고요.
This will make only the first post, which is the LinkedIn post, pass through this path.
이렇게 하면 첫 번째 글인 링크드인 글만 이쪽으로 지나가게 될 겁니다.
Then, click the plus button, and this time select Google Sheets,
그리고 플러스를 누르시고 이번에는 구글 시트
then "Update a row". For the "Spreadsheet ID", select the "News Scrap" sheet that we created earlier.
업데이트 어로우를 선택을 하시고 이 스프레드 시트 아이디에 아까 저희가 만들었던
Select the "News Scrap" sheet.
"뉴스 스크랩" 시트를 선택을 하시고
"Sheet Name": Sheet1, and the "Row number" should be selected as "Row End".
시트네임: 시트1 그리고 로우 넘버는 여기 row end로 선택을 해주시면 되고요.
In the "Values" section, since we're saving the LinkedIn post, add
그리고 values 부분에 지금 링크드인 글을 저장을 하는 거니까 이 링크드인 열에다가
this "fallback match" to the LinkedIn column.
이 fallback match 이 부분을 입력을 해주시면 됩니다.
Click "OK".
OK를 눌러주시고요.
Similarly, for the second path, enter the "i" and put 2 for its value, and then click "OK".
두 번째 역시 필터를 i로 넣어주시고 그리고 값은 2로 넣어주신 다음에 OK를 눌러주세요.
Add "Google Sheets update a row" and
똑같이 구글 시트 update a row를 추가를 하고
set the other options the same as above.
나머지 옵션은 위에 거랑 다 똑같이 설정을 해줍니다.
In the "Values" section, instead of the LinkedIn section, add the "fallback match" to the Twitter section.
그리고 values 부분만 링크드인 부분이 아닌 트위터 부분에다가 fallback match를 넣어주시면 됩니다.
To check if it's working correctly again, click "Run Once" and check the checkbox in the Google Sheet.
다시 한번 제대로 작동하는지 확인하기 위해서 Run Once를 누르고 구글 시트에서 체크박스를 체크를 해볼게요.
It’s detecting the change, ChatGPT is writing the post, and it says that the Google Sheet has been executed.
그러면 이렇게 감지가 되고 있고 ChatGPT가 글을 써주고 구글 시트가 실행됐다고 뜨는데요.
If you go to the sheet, you can see that the LinkedIn post and the Twitter post have been created successfully.
시트로 이동을 해보면 이렇게 링크드인 글과 트위터 글이 잘 생성된 거를 확인을 할 수가 있습니다.
Now that we’ve finished the automatic post creation, let's create the automatic post publishing section.
글 자동 생성 부분이 완성되었으니까 글 자동 발행 부분도 만들어 보겠습니다.
Create a filter in the line section below the first Router.
이 첫 번째 Router 밑에 선 부분에 필터를 만들어줄 건데요.
This time, the path needs to be executed when the "Publish" checkbox is checked.
이번에는 발행 체크박스가 체크될 때 여기가 실행되어야 되니까
Set "Column start" to the 8th column, where the "Publish" checkbox is located.
Column start를 이 발행 체크박스가 있는 열인 8번째 열로 입력을 하고요.
Add an "and rule", and set the "Column end" to the 8th column as well.
and rule 추가한 다음에 Column end도 여덟 번째
Then, set the "Old value" to false and the "Value" to true.
그리고 Old value가 False이고 value값이 True일 때라고 설정을 합니다.
Click the plus button, and add a "Router" from "Flow control".
그리고 여기 플러스를 눌러서 Flow control에 Router를 추가를 해주시고요.
Click the first plus button, search for "LinkedIn,"
그리고 첫 번째 플러스를 눌러서 링크드인을 검색을 하고
and click "Create a user text post" to add it.
여기 Create a user text post를 눌러서 추가를 하겠습니다.
I’ve already connected it to my account, so it appears like this, but you can click the button to connect your account.
저 같은 경우는 미리 연결을 해놔서 이렇게 뜨는데 여러분들은 여기 버튼을 눌러서 연결을 진행해 주시면 됩니다.
In the content section, add the LinkedIn post.
그리고 컨텐츠 부분에 링크드인 포스트 글을 입력을 해주면 되겠죠.
In the Google Sheet, the LinkedIn post is located in the F column,
구글 시트에서 링크드인 포스트가 들어있는 열인 F열을 선택을 해주면 되니까
so add the F column in "Row Value".
이 row value 안에 F열을 입력을 해줍니다.
Click "OK," and the setting is finished.
그리고 OK를 눌러주면 세팅이 끝나고요.
Similarly, search for "X" or "Twitter" and click "Create a post" in X.
이 부분도 역시 X 트위터를 검색을 해서 이 X 안에 있는 Create post를 눌러주시면 됩니다.
I’ve already connected it to my account, so it appears like this.
저 같은 경우는 미리 연결을 해놔서 이렇게 뜨는데
For Twitter, you need to get the API application approved before you can post on Make.
트위터 같은 경우는 사전에 API 신청이 통과되야 메이크에서 이렇게 포스팅을 할 수가 있어요.
It’s a hassle, but applying for the API isn’t difficult. I'll leave a link for the application method.
귀찮긴 하지만 이 API 신청이 어렵지는 않으니까 제가 이 신청 방법을 링크로 남겨둘게요.
Refer to that link and finish connecting your Twitter account. In this text content section,
그걸 참고를 해주시고 트위터 연결을 완료해 주신 다음에 이 Text content 부분에
add the G column, which contains the Twitter content.
트위터 내용이 들어있는 이 G열을 입력을 해주시면 되겠습니다.
Click the G column in "Row Values," add it and click "OK" to finish setting it up.
row values 안에 있는 G열을 눌러서 입력을 해주시고 OK를 누르시면 세팅이 끝납니다.
Now, let's test the automatic publishing.
이제 자동 발행을 테스트를 해보겠습니다.
Click "Run Once", then click "Way for New Data".
Run Once를 누르고 Way for New Data를 누르신 다음에
In the Google Sheet, click the "Publish" checkbox next to the post you want to publish.
구글 시트에서 원하는 글 옆에 발행 체크박스를 누르고
If you go back to the Make scenario, you can see that it’s been executed.
메이크 시나리오를 돌아와 보면 이렇게 실행된 것을 볼 수 있고요.
Let’s go to LinkedIn and check.
실제로 링크드인에 들어가서 확인해 보겠습니다.
You can see that the LinkedIn post has been successfully posted.
이렇게 링크드인 글이 잘 포스팅된 것을 확인할 수가 있고요.
You can also see that the Twitter post has been created successfully.
트위터도 이렇게 글이 잘 생성된 것을 확인할 수가 있습니다.
Now, in the scheduling section below,
이제 이 아래의 스케줄링 부분에
turn on "Immediately as Data Arrives" to have it always detect the Google Sheet. This will finish the system settings.
이 구글 시트를 항상 감지하도록 Immediately as Data Arrives를 켜주시면 시스템 세팅이 끝나는데요.
To delete the existing data, click "Delete Old Data" and then "Delete", then the settings are complete.
기존 데이터는 삭제해주기 위해서 Delete Old Data, Delete를 눌러주시면 세팅이 완료됩니다.
From now on, with just one click of a checkbox,
앞으로는 체크박스 하나만 클릭하면
AI will write and publish the post for you, and you can make your dream of daily posting a reality.
AI가 알아서 글도 쓰고 발행까지 해주니까 꿈에 그리던 1일 1포스팅도 현실로 만드실 수 있을 겁니다.
I'm also using this system to automatically collect the latest news in my areas of interest and post them on social media.
참고로 저는 이 시스템으로 제 관심 분야의 최신 뉴스를 자동으로 수집하고 있고, SNS 포스팅까지 하고 있는데요.
I highly recommend this system, especially to those who want to build their personal brand through various social media channels.
특히 여러 SNS를 통해서 셀프 브랜딩을 하려는 분들에게 강력히 추천드립니다.
Some of you may be worried if the posts written by AI will be good enough.
그리고 AI가 쓴 글이 괜찮을까 이렇게 걱정하시는 분들도 있을 것 같은데요.
Since all posts in this system are saved in the Google Sheet first, you can check and modify them before publishing.
이 시스템은 모든 글이 일단 구글 시트에 저장되기 때문에 발행 전에 검토하고 수정을 할 수 있습니다.
You can refine the prompts while looking at the results.
결과물을 보면서 프롬프트를 조금씩 개선해 나가고
If you’re satisfied with the quality of the generated posts, you can also automate the publishing step.
이 생성된 글 퀄리티가 충분히 마음에 들면 이 발행 단계도 자동화할 수 있는데요.
The method is simple.
방법은 간단합니다.
In the make scenario, just attach the LinkedIn and X modules to the lower part of the update module.
이 메이크 시나리오에서 이 발행 부분 링크드인과 X 모듈을 이 업데이트 모듈 하위에 이렇게 붙여주시면 됩니다.
Then, you can upgrade to a one-step automation where the post creation and publishing are all handled at once.
그러면은 뉴스 선택만 하면 글 작성부터 발행까지 한 번에 처리되는 원스텝 자동화로 업그레이드 하실 수 있습니다.
And, for those of you who followed along till the end, I’m giving away this system for free
그리고 여기까지 따라와 주신 분들을 위해서 이 시스템을 당장 활용할 수 있도록
as a make.com scenario template and prompt examples, so that you can utilize it immediately.
make.com 시나리오 템플릿과 프롬프트 예시를 모두 무료로 드리고 있습니다.
If you need them, you can download them by joining my group chat or subscribing to my newsletter, through the pinned comment.
필요하신 분들은 고정 댓글을 통해서 제 단톡방 커뮤니케이션, 제 뉴스레터를 구독해주시면 바로 다운받을 수 있으니까 참고해주세요.
You can also ask questions and get answers on various AI usage tips in the group chat.
단톡방에서 다양한 AI 활용 팁에 대한 질문 답변도 나누실 수 있으니까
So, if you are struggling with building this type of automation system, please feel free to join.
이런 자동화 시스템 구축에 어려움을 느끼시는 분들도 부담없이 참여해주시면 좋겠습니다.
Today, I explained how to build a system that automates social media posting using make.com.
오늘은 이렇게 메이크닷컴을 활용해서 SNS 포스팅을 자동화하는 시스템을 구축하는 방법을 설명드렸는데요.
If you want to see more AI usage tips, please subscribe and turn on notifications.
더 많은 AI 활용 팁이 궁금하시다면 구독과 알림설정 부탁드립니다.
I'll be back with more helpful information in the next video.
다음 영상에서 더 유익한 정보와 함께 찾아뵙겠습니다.
Thank you for watching.
시청해주셔서 감사합니다.